Guide to the Montana Legislative Council Records 1955-1983
Montana Historical Society
Montana Legislative Council Records
1955-1983
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 319
Montana. Legislative Council
18 linear feet of shelf space
These Montana Legislative Council records (1955-1983) consist of general correspondence, minutes, news releases, organizational materials, and subject files on Council committees and subcommittees.
The Montana Legislative Council was created by the 35th Legislative Assembly in 1957. The Council was composed of six members of the House of Representatives appointed by the Speaker of the House and six members of the Senate appointed by the Senate Committee on Committees. No more than three appointees from each house were to belong to a single party. Appointees served for the length of their term of office or December 31 of the following year, whichever came first. The Council was given the responsibility to "accumulate, compile, analyze, and furnish such information bearing upon matters relating to existing or prospective legislation as may be determined by its own initiative pertaining to important issues of policy and questions of statewide importance...." e.g., consolidation of state bodies, financial administration, efficiency in government, etc. The Council was also to prepare "such bills and resolutions as in its opinion the welfare of the state may require," and present these to the succeeding regular session of the legislature. The Council was given the authority to hold hearings, issue subpoenas, administer oaths, and cause depositions of witnesses to be taken. A primary function of the Council is to undertake research, usually on topics assigned by a joint resolution during the previous legislative session but also on topics the Council determines are important. In most cases the Council appoints a subcommittee composed of legislators and/or, less commonly, private citizens which assumes the primary responsibility for directing staff research. Subcommittees submit their findings, recommendations, and legislation to the full Council which may reject, amend, or accept them. All subcommittee reports adopted by the Council are published and distributed before the legislative session. In addition to conducting studies on specific topics, the Legislative Council staff is available to legislators and standing committees during the legislative session to prepare reports and draft bills on any subject of interest to legislators. This service was inaugurated in 1959. In the same year the Council was designated the Montana Commission on Interstate Cooperation whose purpose is to advance cooperation between Montana and other units of government. The Council also maintains a reference library and answers requests for information "in every possible area." In 1973 the Council was reduced in number to four members from each legislative house who served for two years. In addition, a Committee on Priorities, composed of four members of each legislative house, was established to consider resolutions requesting Council studies and other study requests, prepare a list of priorities, and perform other duties. In 1973 the Council was given the responsibility to publish all laws and resolutions passed or adopted by each session, prepare indices for them, and distribute copies to various agencies and repositories. Executive directors of the Council include Eugene C. Tidball, 1957-1965; Donald L. Sorte, 1965-1969; James W. Van Koten, 1969-1971; Rose E. Weber, 1971-1979; and Diana S. Dowling, 1979-1986.
This collection consists of five series: general correspondence (1959-1975), minutes (1957-1975), news releases (1963-1974), organizational materials (1963, 1971-1974), and subject files (1955-1983). The bulk of the collection consists of subject files which are predominantly the records of committees and subcommittees of the Council; these are arranged alphabetically by the name of the subcommittee. Most, but not all, subcommittees issued reports which were published and distributed. Interfiled with the subcommittee records are the records of statutory committees which received Legislative Council staff assistance. These include, for example, the Administrative Code Committee, the Capitol Building and Planning Committee, the Coal Tax Oversight Committee, the Montana Salary Commission, the Revenue Oversight Committee, and the Water Resources Oversight Committee. Also interfiled with the subcommittee subject files are studies and reports conducted by the Council, not by a subcommittee; these are arranged alphabetically by the subjects of the studies. Maps, photographs, and printed materials have been transferred to the Library Map Collection, the Photo Archives, and the Library respectively.
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Agriculture and state--Montana; Buildings--Design and construction--Montana; Capitols--Montana; District courts--Montana; Education--Finance--Montana; Election law--Montana; Energy development--Montana; Environmental policy--Montana; Equality before the law--Montana; Fire prevention--Montana; Gambling--Montana; Highway planning--Montana; Indians of North America--Legal status, laws, etc.--Montana; Insurance--Montana; Land classification--Montana; Libraries--Montana; Liquor laws--Montana; Local government--Montana; Medical care--Montana; Pesticides--Montana; Probate courts--Montana; Public lands--Montana; Public welfare--Montana; Retirement--Montana; Taxation--Montana; Teachers--Montana; Transportation and state--Montana; Universities and colleges--Montana; Vocational education--Montana; Wages--Montana; Water-supply--Montana; Wild and scenic rivers--Montana; Workers' compensation--Law and legislation--Montana
Montana; Government and Politics
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- General Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous (re Council procedures, study proposals, subcommittee work, etc.), 1959-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 1-4)
- Minutes
  - Minutes, 1957-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 5-9)
- Maps
  - List of maps transferred to the Library Map Collection (Box-folder 1 / 10)
- News Releases
  - News releases, 1963-1974 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
- Organization
  - Rules of procedure, staff responsibilities, 1963, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
- Photographs
  - List of photographs transferred to the Photo Archives (Box-folder 1 / 13)
- Printed Material
  - List of printed material transferred to the Library (Box-folder 1 / 14)
- Subject Files
  - Subcommittee on Administration (re executive reorganization), 1961-1963 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Administrative Code Committee: agencies' statements of reasons for the adoption of rules, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Administrative Code Committee: agendas for meetings, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - Administrative Code Committee: general correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 1 / 18-19)
  - Administrative Code Committee: interoffice correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
  - Administrative Code Committee: interoffice correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Administrative Code Committee: incoming correspondence, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 2 / 2-3)
  - Administrative Code Committee: outgoing correspondence, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 2 / 4-7)
  - Administrative Code Committee: minutes, 1975-1982 (Box-folder 2 / 8-15)
  - Administrative Code Committee: press releases, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 2 / 16)
  - Administrative Code Committee reports re a central office of hearing officers for executive agencies adoption of rules and disputes; publication of the Montana Administrative Register and rules and model rules updating; state legal services; a study of state farms; and a biennial report to the 47th Legislature, 1978-1980, undated (Box-folder 2 / 17)
  - Administrative Code Committee: summaries of Montana Administrative Register and proposed rules, 1975-1979 (Box-folder 2 / 18-20)
  - Subcommittee on Administrative Procedures: correspondence, minutes, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2 / 21)
  - Subcommittee on Administrative Procedures: study of Montana administrative procedures, undated (Box-folder 2 / 22)
  - Subcommittee on Agency Fees, 1964 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
  - Subcommittee on Agricultural Lands, (re preservation of agricultural lands), 1975-1976 (Box-folder 3 / 2-4)
  - Study Committee on Annexation Laws, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 3 / 5-6)
  - Joint Apportionment Committee: see Reapportionment and Rediscticting Commission (Box-folder 3 /)
  - Select Committee on Beef Pricing, 1975 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Study Committee on Branching of Financial Institutions, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 3 / 8-9)
  - Budgeting, Appropriations and Audit Procedures Subcommittee, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 3 / 10)
  - Subcommittee on Building Standards, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 3 / 11)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Business (report and recommendations to the 48th Legislature), 1981-1982 (Box-folder 3 / 12-14)
  - Joint Interim Commission on Business and Industry: see Subcommittee on Wine and Liquor Retailing (Box-folder 3 /)
  - Capitol Building and Planning Committee re Capitol master plan, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 3 / 15)
  - Capitol Building and Planning Committee, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 3 / 16-17)
  - Capitol Complex Committee, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 3 / 18)
  - Coal Tax Oversight Committee: correspondence, 1977-1982 (Box-folder 3 / 19-22)
  - Coal Tax Oversight Committee: minutes, 1975-1982 (Box-folder 4 / 1-5)
  - Coal Tax Oversight Committee: press releases and meeting agendas, 1977-1982 (Box-folder 4 / 6)
  - Coal Tax Oversight Committee: reference material, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 4 / 7-11)
  - Coal Tax Oversight Committee: severance tax challenge, 1980 (Box-folder 4 / 12)
  - Coal Tax Oversight Committee: study plans and staff reports, 1977-1983 (Box-folder 4 / 13-15)
  - Coeducational correctional facilities study, 1977-1972 (Box-folder 4 / 16)
  - Subcommittee on the Constitution, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 4 / 17)
  - Subcommittee on Constitutional Implementation, 1972 (Box-folder 4 / 18)
  - Joint Interim Subcommittee on Constitutions, elections, and federal relations, 1973 (Box-folder 4 / 19-20)
  - Interim Study Committee on Container Deposits, 1979 (Box-folder 4 / 21-22)
  - Task Force on Corrections: correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 5 / 1-2)
  - Task Force on Corrections: minutes, 1982 (Box-folder 5 / 3-4)
  - Task Force on Corrections: press releases and meeting agendas, 1982 (Box-folder 5 / 5)
  - Task Force on Corrections: study plans and staff reports, 1982 (Box-folder 5 / 6)
  - Study Committee on Corrections Policy and Facility Needs: correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 5 / 7-9)
  - Study Committee on Corrections Policy and Facility Needs: minutes, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 5 / 10-12)
  - Study Committee on Corrections Policy and Facility Needs: press releases and meeting agendas, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 5 / 13)
  - Study Committee on Corrections Policy and Facility Needs: study plans and staff reports, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 5 / 14)
  - Study Committee on Corrections Policy and Facility Needs: survey responses, 1980 (Box-folder 5 / 15)
  - Subcommittee on Custodial Institutions, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 5 / 16)
  - Districting and Apportionment Commission: see Reapportionment and Redistricting Commission (Box-folder 5 /)
  - Select Committee on Economic Problems (re air pollution closing of Anaconda Copper Company smelter and refinery, proposed hard rock mineral severance tax, etc.), 1980-1981 (Box-folder 5 / 17-20)
  - Interim Subcommittee on Education (re community college governance), 1977-1978 (Box-folder 6 / 1)
  - Interim Subcommittee on Education: correspondence (re community college governance), 1977-1978 (Box-folder 6 / 2)
  - Interim Subcommittee on Education: minutes (re community college governance), 1977-1978 (Box-folder 6 / 3-4)
  - Subcommittee on Education (re higher eduction), 1959 (Box-folder 6 / 5)
  - Subcommittee on Education (re historic and cultural resources), 1977-1978 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
  - Interim subcommittee on Education (re public libraries, financing and administration of), 1973 (Box-folder 6 / 7)
  - Joint Committee on Education (re school finances), 1981-1982 (Box-folder 6 / 8-10)
  - Subcommittee on Education (re special education), 1973-1974 (Box-folder 6 / 11-12)
  - Subcommittee on Education (re postsecondary vocational-technical governance), 1977-1978 (Box-folder 6 / 13-15)
  - Subcommittee on Election Laws, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 6 / 16)
  - Study Committee on Energy Forecasting, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 6 / 17-19)
  - Subcommittee on Executive Reorganization, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 6 / 20)
  - Subcommittee on Fidelity Bonds and Custodial Institutions (re public officials and employee bonds), 1963-1965 (Box-folder 6 / 21)
  - Subcommittee on Finance and Claims (re bond issues in Montana and Swan River Youth Forest Camp), 1973 (Box-folder 6 / 22)
  - Subcommittee on Finance and Claims (re bond issues in Montana and Swan River Youth Forest Camp), 1973 (Box-folder 7 / 1)
  - Subcommittee on Finance and Claims (re institutions), 1974 (Box-folder 7 / 2)
  - Subcommittee on Fire Laws, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 3)
  - Subcommittee on Fire Laws (re Fire Service Academy), 1976 (Box-folder 7 / 4)
  - Subcommittee on Fire Laws: minutes, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 5-6)
  - Subcommittee on Fire Laws: reports, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 7)
  - Subcommittee on Fiscal Administration, 1959-1962 (Box-folder 7 / 8-9)
  - Subcommittee on Fiscal Analysis, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 7 / 10)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Fish and Game, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 7 / 11-12)
  - Fort Union Coal Conference: correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 13)
  - Fort Union Coal Conference: grant proposals submitted to the National Science Foundation, 1975 (Box-folder 7 / 14)
  - Fort Union Coal Conference: papers presented, 1975 (Box-folder 7 / 15)
  - Fort Union Coal Conference: reports, 1976 (Box-folder 7 / 16)
  - Fort Union Coal Conference: Air Quality Task Force, 1976 (Box-folder 7 / 17)
  - Fort Union Coal Conference: Common Data Element and Information Exchange Task Force, 1976 (Box-folder 7 / 18)
  - Fort Union Coal Conference: Energy Development, Regulation, and Plant Siting Task Force, 1976 (Box-folder 7 / 19)
  - Fort Union Coal Conference: Reclamation and Land Use Task Force, 1976 (Box-folder 7 / 20)
  - Fort Union Coal Conference: Social and Economic Impact Task Force, 1976 (Box-folder 7 / 21)
  - Fort Union Coal Conference: Taxation of Energy Resources Task Force, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 22)
  - Fort Union Coal Conference: Water Allocation and Quality Problems Task Force, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 23)
  - Subcommittee on Fossil Fuel Taxation, 1974 (Box-folder 7 / 24-25)
  - Select Committee on Gambling, 1973 (Box-folder 8 / 1-3)
  - Subcommittee on Governmental Efficiency, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 8 / 4)
  - Special committee to investigate the Highway Department (re efficiency in the engineer's office and the administration of highway funds, Horace B. William's case against the department for unwarranted dismissal, and the routing of Interstate 90), 1958-1960 (Box-folder 8 / 5-7)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Highways, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 8 / 8-11)
  - Joint Interim Subcommittee on Highways and Transportation, 1973 (Box-folder 8 / 12)
  - Subcommittee on Home Rule, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 8 / 13)
  - Interim committee on Human Services: correspondence (re human services delivery system in Montana), 1977-1978 (Box-folder 8 / 14-18)
  - Interim committee on Human Services: minutes (re human services delivery system in Montana), 1977 (Box-folder 8 / 19)
  - Interim committee on Human Services: minutes (re human services delivery system in Montana), 1978 (Box-folder 9 / 1-2)
  - Interim committee on Human Services: press releases and meeting agendas (re human services delivery system in Montana), 1977-1978 (Box-folder 9 / 3)
  - Interim committee on Human Services: study plans and staff reports (re human services delivery system in Montana), 1977-1978 (Box-folder 9 / 4-5)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Human Services (re a proposal for the reorganization of Montana's youth services), 1981-1982 (Box-folder 9 / 6-7)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Human Services: minutes (re a proposal for the reorganization of Montana's youth services), 1981-1982 (Box-folder 9 / 8-10)
  - Subcommittee on Human Services (re survey of the management and services of the Montana Department of Institutions), 1981-1982 (Box-folder 9 / 11)
  - Subcommittee on Income Taxation, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 9 / 12)
  - Select Committee on Indian Affairs, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 9 / 13-15)
  - Committee on Indian Legal Jurisdication, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 9 / 16-17)
  - Subcommittee on Insurance, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 9 / 18)
  - Select Committee on Inter-School Activities (re the Montana High School Association and Montana inter-school activities), 1974 (Box-folder 9 / 19-21)
  - Select Committee on Inter-School Activities (re the Montana High School Association and Montana inter-school activities), 1974 (Box-folder 10 / 1)
  - Subcommittee on Investments (re the investment of public funds), 1963-1964 (Box-folder 10 / 2-3)
  - Subcommittee on Judiciary (re alcoholic beverage control statutes and the equality of the sexes), 1974 (Box-folder 10 / 4)
  - Subcommittee on Judiciary (re appellate court delay), 1981-1982 (Box-folder 10 / 5)
  - Subcommittee on Judiciary (re district courts), 1975-1976 (Box-folder 10 / 6-10)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Judiciary: correspondence (re district courts: indigent defense and prosecutorial services), 1981-1982 (Box-folder 10 / 11-13)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Judiciary: minutes (re district courts: indigent defense and prosecutorial services), 1981-1982 (Box-folder 10 / 14-15)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Judiciary: press releases, meeting agendas, and survey (re district courts: indigent defense and prosecutorial services), 1981-1982 (Box-folder 10 / 16)
  - Joint Committee on Judiciary: study plans and staff reports (re district courts: indigent defense and prosecutorial services), 1981-1982 (Box-folder 10 / 17)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Judiciary: study plans and staff reports (re district courts: indigent defense and prosecutorial services), 1982 (Box-folder 10 / 18)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Judiciary (re no-fault insurance), 1973-1974 (Box-folder 10 / 19)
  - Joint Committee on Judiciary (re sovereign immunity), 1974-1976 (Box-folder 11 / 1-3)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Judiciary (re uniform probate code), 1973-1974 (Box-folder 11 / 4)
  - Subcommittee on Justices of the Peace Courts, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 11 / 5)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Legislative Administration, 1973 (Box-folder 11 / 6)
  - House Subcommittee on Legislative Administration, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 11 / 7)
  - Legislative Fiscal Review Committee, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 11 / 8-10)
  - Legislative Fiscal Review Committee (includes brief history of the committee, 1983), 1970, 1983 (Box-folder 11 / 11)
  - Subcommittee on Legislative Improvement, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 11 / 12-16)
  - Subcommittee on Legislative Modernization, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 11 / 17)
  - Legislative procedures study, 1961 (Box-folder 11 / 18)
  - Subcommittee on Legislative Rules, 1963 (Box-folder 11 / 19)
  - Subcommittee on Liquor Control, 1959-1964 (Box-folder 11 / 20-21)
  - Subcommittee on Liquor Control, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 12 / 1-2)
  - Subcommittee on Local Government, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 12 / 3)
  - Subcommittee on Local Government Laws, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 12 / 4-6)
  - Select Committee on Medical Malpractice, 1976 (Box-folder 12 / 7-9)
  - Joint Interim Subcommittee on Natural Resources and Agriculture: see Subcommittee on Agricultural Lands (Box-folder 12 /)
  - Interim Committee on Needs for Legislative Employees, 1968 (Box-folder 12 / 10)
  - Subcommittee on Occupational Licensing and Teacher Certification, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 12 / 11-15)
  - Subcommittee on Personnel and Retirement Systems, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 12 / 16-17)
  - Subcommittee on Pesticides, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 12 / 18-19)
  - Subcommittee on Priorities and Rules: see Subcommittee on Rules (Box-folder 12 /)
  - Prison Subcommittee, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 13 / 1-2)
  - Subcommittee on Property Classification Law and Agency Fees, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 13 / 3-4)
  - Subcommittee on Property Taxation, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 13 / 5)
  - Subcommittee on Public Health, Welfare, and Safety (re local vs. state health service, etc.), 1973-1974 (Box-folder 13 / 6)
  - Study Committee on Public Retirement Systems, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 13 / 7-9)
  - Subcommittee on Public Welfare, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 13 / 10-11)
  - Subcommittee on the Railraod Commission (re utility rates and consumer protective legislation, the Public Service Commission, etc.), 1969-1972 (Box-folder 13 / 12-15)
  - Reapportionment and Redistricting Commission, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 13 / 16-18)
  - Recodification of the Revised Codes of Montana, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 13 / 19)
  - Subommittee on Retirement Systems and Occupational Licensing Boards (re retirement systems for policemen and firefighters), 1964-1966 (Box-folder 14 / 1)
  - Retirement systems for public employees in fire protection and law enforcement, 1974 (Box-folder 14 / 2)
  - Subcommittee on Rules, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 14 / 3-4)
  - Revenue Oversight Committee: correspondence, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 14 / 5-8)
  - Revenue Oversight Committee: minutes, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 14 / 9-16)
  - Revenue Oversight Committee: study plans and staff reports, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 14 / 17-18)
  - Revenue Oversight Committee: correspondence, bill drafts, etc. (re revision of Montana's property tax classification system, and other reports), 1977-1978 (Box-folder 14 / 19)
  - Revenue Oversight Committee: minutes (re revision of Montana's property tax classification system, and other reports), 1977-1979 (Box-folder 15 / 1-4)
  - Subcommittee on Roll Call and Sound System Equipment, 1971 (Box-folder 15 / 5)
  - Subcommittee on Rules, 1972 (Box-folder 15 / 6)
  - Montana Salary Commission (includes draft minority report, 1973), 1973-1974 (Box-folder 15 / 7)
  - Montana Salary Commission (report and recommendations), 1975-1976: see Box 20, folders 20-29 (Box-folder 15 /)
  - Montana Salary Commission, 1978, 1980, 1982 (Box-folder 15 / 8-11)
  - Subcommittee on School Construction - Laboratories, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 15 / 12-13)
  - Subcommittee on School Foundation Program, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 15 / 14-15)
  - Subcommittee on School Law Revision, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 15 / 16)
  - Subcommittee on School Laws, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 15 / 17)
  - Study Committee on Seed Certification, 1980 (Box-folder 15 / 18)
  - Subcommittee on Self-Insurance, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 15 / 19)
  - Subcommittee on State Administration, 1973 (Box-folder 15 / 20)
  - Select Committee on State Employee Pay, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 15 / 21)
  - Select Committee on State Employee Pay: minutes, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 15 / 22-23)
  - Select Committee on State Employee Pay: reports, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 15 / 24-25)
  - Subcommittee on State Laboratories, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 16 / 1)
  - Subcommittee on State Lands and Investments (re grazing lands), 1958-1962 (Box-folder 16 / 2-3)
  - Subcommittee on State Legal Services and Election Laws, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 16 / 4)
  - Subcommittee on State Legal Services and Election Laws: correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 16 / 5-6)
  - Subcommittee on State Legal Services and Election Laws: minutes, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 16 / 7-8)